FIROZ ANSARI

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

CONTACT

07749269788

firozansar@gmail.com

www.firozansari.info

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Android development

iOS development

.NET / Python/ JavaScript

PUBLISHED APPS

Meerkat Android App

https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.ctm.cinema&hl=en_GB&gl=US

Stagecoach Bus Android App

hhttps://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.stagecoach.stagecoachbus

TopCashback apps

https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=uk.co.topcashback.topcashback

Gone For Good app

https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.reasondigital.goneforgood

EDUCATION

MSc Computing (Distinction)

Manchester Metropolitan University

2012-2013

Course modules included MSc Project, Enterprise Programming, Advanced Database System, Information System Management and Strategy, Object Oriented Programming, Multimedia and Internet Application.

BA (Honours)

University of Calcutta

1996-1999

English Literature, Economics and Political Science

PROFILE

I am an experienced mobile software engineer with 8+ years of commercial native mobile development experience which includes over 10 published Android apps including app which ranked in top 10 in the UK (Stagecoach Bus app currently ranked 9th in Map and Navigation section in the UK), app which is highly rated in the play store (TopCashback UK app 4.5/5 based on over 16K reviews) and app which won award (Gone For Good app won Best not for profit award at Big Chip Awards 2016)

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer

Compare the Market / BGL Group, London

2021-present

Although I started as a mid-senior Software Engineer, I got promoted to Senior Software Engineer. Currently I'm leading the work of designing and developing Android libraries written in Kotlin in the platform team. For example, I worked on the User-Session library module which encapsulates all the functionality related to the CTM app users and their identification, authorization, and authentication. I have also helped the Android Experience team integrate those libraries into the Meerkat Android app. My other notable work in the platform team includes working on improving/automating CI/CD workflows, increasing test automation coverage, writing and publishing documentation (using Dokka) etc.

Android Tech Lead / Senior Software Engineer

Stagecoach Group Plc, Manchester

2018-2020

As Android Tech Lead, I managed and mentored a team of developers while working hands-on. Apart from maintaining and adding functionalities to existing Stagecoach apps (Stagecoach UK Bus app, Oxford Tube app etc.), I contributed to the vision and long-term technical strategy. The UK Bus app is currently downloaded more than a million times and 11th in the Google Play UK maps and navigation category (November, 2020). My most notable contribution to the app was the implementation of a live map displaying real time bus movement features in the current Stagecoach Bus Android app. During COVID-19 crisis, I implemented "busy bus" functionality which helped customers visualise how busy a bus was for social distancing purposes. Another notable contribution of mine was the Google Pay integration in the app during the Google Pay event at Google London office where I also did a technical presentation on it.

Mobile Developer

TopCashback Ltd, Horwich, Greater Manchester

2016-2018

At Topcashback, I was solely responsible for improving and maintaining the TopCashback Android apps (UK, US and Indian versions), adding functionalities and giving users high quality and innovative experience. The UK app has already been downloaded more than half a million times and ranked consistently among the top 50 shopping apps in the UK. During my time, 130K+ TopCashback members used the app regularly every month with 99.9% crash free app sessions. I contributed not only to the app user experience redesign, but also wrote clean and efficient code using SOLID principles using the latest Android APIs and libraries to make it robust and successful.

I had also experienced of working at the .NET mobile server consisting of mobile service and cashback data service written in C#/VB.NET and a portal for bespoke mobile contents using Angular and .NET Core 2.0.

Apart from my usual development duties, I have also done interviews for developers and mentored junior developers in the mobile team.

